A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007-2009 (bulk 2007)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007-2009 (bulk 2007)
The Library of Virginia
51144 and 52129
20.52 cubic feet (63 boxes) and 4931 emails
Virginia Tech Review Panel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This collection includes health records, legal advice, and personal information that is restricted for 75 years by the Code of Virginia (Virginia Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act, Virginia Public Records Act, and the Virginia Health Records Privacy Act).
Acquisition Information
Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 East Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, accession 51144 transferred on 9 January 2014.
Gordon Davies papers, accession 52129, gift received on 15 September 2017.
Custodial History
The records of the Virginia Tech Review Panel were compiled by the law firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP. They received materials from Panel members, TriData, and their own staff members who provided legal advice to the Panel. Housed in 17 oversized boxes, Skadden mailed these files to the Office of the Governor in December 2007. These records, and an additional four boxes of records created by the Kaine administration, remained in the custody of the Governor's Office until January 2014 when they were transferred to the Library of Virginia. One CD of electronic records listed in the Skadden inventory was missing when the records arrived at the Library.
Gordon Davies donated additional records to the Library of Virginia on 15 September 2017. These records were added to Gordon Davies's papers in Series I.A. Records of Gordon Davies.
Historical Information
On 16 April 2007, Seung Hui Cho killed 32 people and injured at least 17 others before turning the gun on himself. The massacre at Virginia Tech is one of the deadliest shooting incidents by a single gunman in United States history. At the time of the shooting, Governor Tim Kaine had just arrived in Tokyo, Japan, for a trade mission. Kaine immediately returned to Virginia to deliver the convocation at Virginia Tech the next day. On 19 April 2007, Kaine commissioned the Virginia Tech Review Panel "to conduct an independent, thorough, and objective incident review of the tragedy at Virginia Tech and to make recommendations regarding improvements that can be made in the Commonwealth's laws, policies, procedures, systems and institutions, as well as those of other governmental entities and private providers." The members of the panel were:
Panel Chair Col. Gerald Massengill, a retired Virginia State Police Superintendent who led the Commonwealth's law enforcement response to the 11 September 2001, attack on the Pentagon and the sniper attacks that affected the Commonwealth in 2002.
Panel Vice Chair Dr. Marcus L. Martin, Professor of Emergency Medicine, Assistant Dean of the School of Medicine and Associate Vice President for Diversity and Equity at the University of Virginia.
Gordon Davies, former Director of the State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (1977-1997) and President of the Kentucky Council on Postsecondary Education (1998-2002).
Dr. Roger L. Depue, a 20-year veteran of the FBI and the founder, past president and CEO of The Academy Group, Inc., a forensic behavioral sciences services company providing consultation, research, and investigation of aberrant and violent behavioral problems.
Carroll Ann Ellis, MS, Director of the Fairfax County Police Department's Victim Services Division, a faculty member at the National Victim Academy, and a member of the American Society of Victimology.
The Honorable Tom Ridge, former Governor of Pennsylvania (1995-2001) and Member of the U.S. House of Representatives (1983-1995) who was also the first U.S. Secretary of Homeland Security (2003-2005).
Dr. Aradhana A. "Bela" Sood, Professor of Psychiatry and Pediatrics, Chair of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Medical Director of the Virginia Treatment Center for Children at VCU Medical Center.
The Honorable Diane Strickland, former judge of the 23rd Judicial Circuit Court in Roanoke County (1989-2003) and co-chair of the Boyd-Graves Conference on issues surrounding involuntary mental commitment.
Kaine formalized the Tech Panel's charge in Executive Order 53 (2007) issued on 18 June 2007.
TriData, a division of System Planning Corporation, provided staff support for the Virginia Tech Review Panel. In April 2007, Col. Gerald Massengill, Chairman of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, requested that Governor Tim Kaine retain TriData on behalf of the Commonwealth to assist the panel in completing an independent analysis of the circumstances of the 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech. TriData provided research, staff support and logistics for the Panel. TriData assisted the panel in collecting, organizing, and analyzing relevant information needed to develop a detailed factually analysis of the shooting and provide recommendations to Governor Kaine. TriData also assisted with writing, editing, and compiling the panel's report to the governor.
TriData staff that assisted the Panel included: Philip Schaenman, panel staff director; Hollis Stambaugh, panel staff deputy director; Jim Kudla, panel public information officer; Dr. Harold Cohen; Darryl Sensenig; Paul Flippin; Teresa Copping; Maria Argabright; Shania Flagg; Lucius Lamar III; Rachel Merson; and Jim Gray.
On 29 May 2007, the panel engaged the international law firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and From LLP to provide legal advice on a pro bono basis. Virginia Attorney General Robert McDonnell recommended that Governor Kaine appoint a special counsel for the panel in order to avoid any potential conflict of interest.
The panel held four public meetings: on 10 May 2007 in Richmond, 21 May 2007 at Virginia Tech, 11 June 2007 at George Mason University in Fairfax, and 18 July 2007 at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. The panel held a closed session on 19 July 2007 in Charlottesville to consult with counsel and discuss confidential matters and records. The panel began writing their report in July with assistance and editing by TriData and Skadden.
The Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel was released on 30 August 2007. It revealed deficiencies in the mental health care system, campus security and gun laws. The panel made more than 70 recommendations directed to colleges, universities, mental health providers, law enforcement officials, emergency service providers and law makers. The General Assembly passed legislation to reform mental health commitment laws and campus security policies. One major recommendation by the panel was defeated: requiring background checks for all firearms purchases at gun shows.
In April 2008, the commonwealth reached an $11 million financial settlement with 24 families of students and faculty who were killed or injured during the Virginia Tech shooting. The commonwealth agreed to provide monetary pay outs, medical care and information on the shooting in exchange for the families waiving their right to sue. Two families did not accept the settlement and filed a civil suit in 2009. The discovery of Cho's counseling center records in July 2009 as well as other concerns by family members about the panel's official timeline for 16 April 2007 lead to calls for the panel to reconvene. Kaine did not reconvene the panel but agreed to have the report revised to reflect new details that had surfaced since 2007. The first addendum was completed by TriData in November 2009. Additional corrections to the addendum were made in December 2009.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Tech Review Panel Records, 2007-2009 (bulk 2007), are organized into five series. Series have designated for Files of Virginia Tech Review Panel Members, Files of TriData, Files of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, Files of the Office of the Governor, and Freedom of Information Act Request. These records document Virginia's official investigation into the 16 April 2007 mass shooting at Virginia Tech.
This is a hybrid collection. The paper records are available in the Library's Archives Research Room during normal business hours. The Virginia Tech Review Panel emails are accessible online via Digitool under State Archives Collections. Researchers are strongly encouraged to read the email Tips Sheets before using the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Files of Virginia Tech Review Panel Members, 2007-2009:
Subseries A. Records of Gordon Davies, 2007-2009
Subseries B. Records of Dianne Strickland, 2007
Subseries C. Records of Carroll Ann Ellis, 2007
Subseries D. Records of Gerald Massengill, 2007.
Series II. Files of TriData, a Division of System Planning Corporation, 2007:
Subseries A. Drafts of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, 2007
Subseries B. Confidential Seung Hui Cho Documents, 2007 (transmitted)
Subseries C. Collected Documents Related to the Investigation, 2007.
Series III. Files of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007:
Subseries A. General Files
Subseries B. Files of Bradley Marcus, 2007
Subseries C. Files of Ian Erickson, 2007
Subseries D. Files of Mike Kelly, 2007
Subseries E. Files of Michael Tierney, 2007
Subseries F. Files of Amy Sabrin, 2007
Subseries G. Files of Rich Brusca, 2007
Subseries H. Files of Anne Kim, 2007.
Series IV. Files of the Office of the Governor, 2007-2009.
Series V. Freedom of Information Act Request, 2007.
Related Material
The Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal includes over 13,000 Virginia Tech-related emails from Kaine administration staff members, including Tim Kaine, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Marc Follmer and Kate Paris. Subjects of these emails include the creation, work, and report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel; meetings and correspondence between Kaine administration officials and family members of those killed or injured during the shooting; and implementation of the 2008 settlement agreement. Documents that fall under the category of attorney-client privilege, mediation and settlement discussions, and privacy-protected information such as medical records have all been restricted or redacted.
The Virginia Tech Review Panel Archived Web Site, 2007 was used by the Virginia Tech Review Panel to gather comments and to inform the public about scheduled meetings and other developments.
Video of the Virginia Tech Review Panel's public meetings on 10 May 2007, 11 June 2007 morning session, 11 June 2007 afternoon session, and Governor Tim Kaine's acceptance of the Panel's report on 30 August 2007 is available online courtesy of C-SPAN.
Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007
Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech: Addendum to the Report of the Review Panel, November-December 2009
The Tragedy at Virginia Tech Web Archive Collection, 2007-2012 captures Virginia government websites related to the shooting at Virginia Tech on Monday, April 16, 2007. This collection includes audio excerpts from press conferences held on Tuesday, April 17, audio excerpts from the Convocation ceremony held on Tuesday, April 17, and a video stream of the entire Convocation. Also included is a list of the victims.
The Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Anne Holton), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Bob McDonnell and William C. Mims), two statewide officials elected in the same cycle as Governor Kaine.
Contents List
- Series I. Files of Virginia Tech Review Panel Members, 2007-2009., Extent: 1.94 cubic feet (7 boxes) and 999 emails. (Box 1-4 and 58-60)
  The Files of the Virginia Tech Review Panel Members series documents the work of individual members of the Panel. Series is arranged into four subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Records of Gordon Davies; B. Records of Dianne Strickland; C. Records of Carroll Ann Ellis; and D. Records of Gerald Massengill. The series consists of agendas, agreements, correspondence, email, drafts, handouts, memorandum, notes, presentations, and reports. This collection includes health records, legal advice, and personal information that are restricted for 75 years by the Code of Virginia (Virginia Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act, Virginia Public Records Act, Virginia Health Records Privacy Act). Restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the collection.
  Additional individual Panel member records can be found in Series II. Files of TriData, especially Subseries A. Drafts of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, 2007, and Series III. Files of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007, especially Subseries G. Files of Rich Brusca.
  This is a hybrid series. The paper records are available in the Library's Archives Research Room during normal business hours. The Virginia Tech Review Panel emails are accessible online via Digitool under State Archives Collections. Researchers are strongly encouraged to read the email Tips Sheets before using the collection.
  - Series I. Files of Virginia Tech Review Panel Members, Subseries A. Records of Gordon Davies, 2007-2008., Extent: 1.06 cu. ft. (box 1, 58-60) and 412 emails
    This subseries is further divided into: A.I. Virginia Tech Review Panel Records, 2007, and A.II. Personal Papers, 2007-2009.
    - Series I.A.I. Virginia Tech Review Panel Records, 2007., Extent: 0.35 cu. ft. (box 1) and 412 emails
      Gordon Davies Virginia Tech Review Panel records are housed in one box. It also contains 412 number of emails. Gordon Davies was the former Director of the State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (1977-1997) and President of the Kentucky Council on Postsecondary Education (1998-2002).
      Paper records include: drafts of the Panel's reports with handwritten edits/notes; and working files from Panel meetings including meeting notes.
      Davies sent and receieved 412 emails between April and September 2007. There are seven confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Davies' unrestricted email is accessible online.
      Email subjects include: leak of panel report to the New York Times; media stories on the shooting, work of the Panel, and release of Panel report; panel meetings; press inquiries; writing of report; and proposed interviews.
      Notable email includes: Cho's "shooting story" written for a class in fiction writing; email from Phil Schaenman to the panel, dated 13 June 2007, outlining preliminary report schedule; and email thread dated 29-30 August 2007 on the leak of the final report to the New York Times and the Governor's Office decision to post it online.
      Email correspondents include: Teresa Copping, Roger Depue, Carroll Ann Ellis, Jim Kudla, Bill Leighty, Marcus Martin, Gerald Massengill, Lenwood McCoy, Phil Schaenman, Amy Sabrin, Bela Sood, Hollis Stambaugh, and Diane Strickland.
      - Virginia Tech Review Panel Report drafts, August 2007. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Tech Review Panel Report drafts, August 2007. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - First Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 10 May 2007. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Second Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 21 May 2007. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Third Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 11 June 2007. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Tri-Data Meeting-Security and Communications, Virginia Tech, 20 June 2007. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Fourth Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 18 July 2007. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - College and University COOP Subcommittee Notes, 26 July 2007. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Notes from meeting at Virginia Tech, 3 August 2007. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Governor's Campus Security Conference, 13 August 2007. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Articles and Reference Material, April-June 2007. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Series I.A.II. Personal Papers, 2007-2009 (Accession 52129)., Extent: 0.71 cu. ft. (boxes 59-60)
      Gordon Davies personal papers are housed in three boxes. Gordon Davies was the former Director of the State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (1977-1997) and President of the Kentucky Council on Postsecondary Education (1998-2002).
      Davies' personal papers contain some Virginia Tech Review Panel records including legal advice to the panel, meeing notes, copy of the final report, and newspaper clippings. The meeting notes are not clearly identified. Some of the dates suggest they are Panel meeting notes. Others may be interview notes. The remainder of Davies personal papers contain records from conference meetings (agendas, presenations, and prepared remarks) he attended and articles he wrote about the Virginia Tech shooting. Restricted material (attorney-client communications and attorney work product) are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
      - Notes, undated. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Notes, 19 June 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Meeting Notes, American Council on Education, 27 June 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Tech Panel thoughts, 27 June 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Draft Notes, 1 July 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Notes, 10 July 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Notes from Fourth Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 18 July 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Notes from Fourth Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 19 July 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Interview Notes from Carroll Ann Ellis, 20 July 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Interview Notes from Bela Sood, 24 July 2007. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 58, Folder 2)
      - Memorandum to James A. Hyatt, Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer, Virginia Tech, from Larry Hincker, Associate Vice President for University Relations, Communications related to April 16, 4 June 2007`. (Box 58, Folder 3)
      - Notes from meeting with faculty and administrators from several community colleges that are part of the Virginia Commmunity College System, 15 May 2007. (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Meeting Notes, Hearing at Washington and Lee University with Council of Independent Colleges in Virginia, Inc., charied by Dr. Gordon Davies and Diane Strickland, 15 June 2007. (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Office of the Inspector General for Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Investigation of April 16, 2007 (OIG Report 140-07), 2007 (2 copies). (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Report to the President of the United States on Issues Raised by the Virginia Tech Tragedy, 13 June 2007. (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous Reference Materials, 2002, 2005-2007. (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 2007. (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Newspaper Clippings about Virginia Tech Shooting, 2007-2009. (Box 58, Folder 5)
      - Conferences and Presentations
        - National Lt. Governors Association Annual Meeting, Remarks of Gordon K. Davies, 25 July 2007. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - National Council of State Directors of Community Colleges, 2007 Summer Conference, Williamsburg, Virginia, 5-8 August 2007. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - C-SPAN Washington Journal, September 2007. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Michigan Community College Association Security and Emergency Management Workshop, 1 February 2008. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Campus Safety Forum, Simpson College, Iowa, 5 June 2008. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Homeland Defense Journal Training Conference, The School Security and Safety Regional Training Symposium, Denver, Colorado, 16-17 June 2008. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - State Higher Education Executive Officers (SHEEO) Higher Education Policy Conference, San Diego, California, 14 August 2008. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Fifth Annual Governor's Homeland Security Conference, Iowa, 30 September-1 October 2008. (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Unidentified Presentation Notes? undated. (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - "Reflections on the Virginia Tech Shootings," RPECnews, November/December 2007. (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - "Connecting the Dots: Lessons From the Virginia Tech Shootings," Change, January/February 2008. (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Review Panel, presented by Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007 [RESTRICTED]. (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Series I. Files of Virginia Tech Review Panel Members, Subseries B. Records of Diane Strickland, 2007., Extent: 0.98 cu. ft. (boxes 2-4) and 256 emails
    This subseries is housed in three boxes. It also contains 256 emails that can be accessed online. Diane Strickland was a former judge of the 23rd Judicial Circuit Court in Roanoke County (1989-2003) and co-chair of the Boyd-Graves Conference on issues surrounding involuntary mental commitment.
    Paper records include: Seung-Hui Cho's health records from Virginia Tech's Schiffert Health Center and Cook Counseling Center; Seung-Hui Cho's education records from Virginia Tech that includes admission information, university transcript, emails between members of English Department about Cho as well as examples of his writing assignments; Seung-Hui Cho's education records from the Fairfax County Public Schools; Seung-Hui Cho's medical records from Carilion New River Valley Medical Center and Carilion Saint Alban's Behavioral Health; outline and drafts of the Virginia Tech Review Panel report; and "Fatal School Shootings in the United States, 1966-2007," prepared by Skadden in 2007. Restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the collection.
    Strickland sent and receieved 256 emails between April and September 2007. There are 13 confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Strickland's unrestricted email is accessible online.
    Email subjects include: campus gun policies; Cho's mental health history, including drafts of chapter, "Mental Health History of Seung Hui Cho"; Cho's student writings from Professor Robert Hickock's class; gun control; Panel meetings; writing of report, including concerns about reviewing drafts and finishing work by 23 August 2007; and interviews (proposed lists and notes).
    Notable email includes: email thread between Roger Depue and Bela Sood, dated 22-23 August 2007, detailing their differences of opinion about Cho's mental health; email from Lenwood McCoy, dated 26 August 2007, to Diane Strickland transmitting Cho's story from Professor Robert Hickock's class; two emails from John Eide, dated 17 July 2007, containing Facebook messages Eide received from Cho in the fall of 2006; and email from Hollis Stambaugh, dated 11 June 2007, to the panel forwarding a letter from John Hammaren, father of Caitlin Hammaren.
    Email correspondents include: Richard Bonnie, Richard Brusca, Gordon Davies, Roger Depue, Carroll Ann Ellis, Jim Kudla, Marcus Martin, Gerald Massengill, Lenwood McCoy, Phil Schaenman, Amy Sabrin, Bela Sood, and Hollis Stambaugh,